<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="resume.xsl"?>

<resume>
    <introduction>
        <firstname>Karim</firstname>
        <lastname>El Shenawy</lastname>
        <address>
            <city>Milton</city>
            <province>Ontario</province>
            <postal>L9T0C9</postal>
        </address>
        <contactno>14168244516</contactno>
        <email>elshenak@mcmaster.ca</email>
        <linkedin>/elshenak</linkedin>
        <github>/elninokr</github>
        <website>elninokr.com</website>
    </introduction>
    <work>
        <postion>
            <title>Security Development Student</title>
            <company>Blackberry QNX</company>
            <date>Jan 20' - April 20'</date>
            <description>
                    • Designing and integrating unit test cases in Python using Pytest framework for the core QNX Operating System
                    • Implementing a Jenkins Pipeline to setup automated test environments
                    • Assisting Developers in developing automation tools in C and resolving defects
            </description>
        </position>
        <postion>
            <title>Student, Information System Cybersecurity</title>
            <company>Canadian Natural Resources Limited (CNRL)</company>
            <date>May 19' - Aug 19'</date>
            <description>
                    • Developed a Phishing Tool that sends fraudulent email campaigns against 15 000 employees as a part of phishing awareness training. Automated results into CSV reports. Built using Python and PHP
                    • Devised weekly Security Scans using Nessus Professional to ensure CIS compliance and identify vulnerabilities
                    • Managed Forescout CounterACT and Palo Alto Panorama Firewall in order to monitor and control internet traffic and to protect production systems
                    • Generated reports and tickets containing QIDs, CVEs, and other vulnerabilities for the mitigation teams
            </description>
        </position>
    </work>
    <skills>
        <programming>Python, Java, C, C++, JavaScript, MATLAB, Bash, PowerShell, Verilog, HTML, CSS</programming>
        <framework>Django, React, Bootstrap, NumPy, OpenCV, TensorFlow</framework>
        <technologies>Git, LaTeX, Eclipse IDE, SVN, db2, MySQL</technologies>
        <sectools>Nessus, Wireshark, Metasploit, Nmap, Burp Suite</sectools>
        <interests>Software Development, Cryptography, Machine Learning, Computer and Network Security</interests>
    </skills>
    <projects>
        <project>
            <name>Stock Predictor</name>
            <language>Python</language>
            <content>
                    • Developed a web application that displays and analyses current stock prices and currency exchange values using the Alpha Vantage API which generates current and historical data
                    • Utilizes Long-short term memory (LSTM) Recurrent Neural Network to give predications of future stock prices
                    • Built front-end using Django framework.
            </content>
        </project>
        <project>
            <name>Least Bit Encryption</name>
            <language>Python</language>
            <content>
                Developed a Linux Command line tool application that encrypt and decrypts text in images using the Least Significant Bit algorithm, built using OpenCV.
            </content>
        </project>
        <project>
            <name>Cipho</name>
            <language>Java</language>
            <content>
                Developed a Windows application that encrypts and decrypts text and textfiles using various cryptographic algorithms and performs Statistical methods for decryption.
            </content>
        </project>
    </projects>
    <education>
        <school>
            <name>McMaster University</name>
            <degree>Bachelor of Engineering in Software Engineering w/ CO-OP</degree>
            <date>Sept 16' - May 21'</date>
            <minor>Mathematics Minor</minor>
        </school>
    </education>
</resume>
